<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fountain of life, or life in its derivation from Christ. In a sermon preached at the funeral of that honoured lady, the Lady Jane Reade, the relict of Sir John Reade, (sometimes whil'st he lived) of Sorangle in Lincolnshire, knight. By Edmund Pinchbeck, B.D.</title>
            <author>[Pinchbeck, Edmund].</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90706</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2244</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E679_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206749</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865855</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865855</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118106</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90706)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118106)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 105:E679[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fountain of life, or life in its derivation from Christ. In a sermon preached at the funeral of that honoured lady, the Lady Jane Reade, the relict of Sir John Reade, (sometimes whil'st he lived) of Sorangle in Lincolnshire, knight. By Edmund Pinchbeck, B.D.</title>
                  <author>[Pinchbeck, Edmund].</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T.R. &amp; E.M. for Humfrey Tuckey, at the black-spread Eagle in Fleetstreet, over against St. Dunstans Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The fountain of life, or life in its derivation from Christ.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "nouemb 7th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118106:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FOUNTAIN OF LIFE, OR Life in its derivation from CHRIST.</p>
            <p>In a SERMON Preached at the Funeral of that honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lady, the Lady <hi>JANE READE,</hi> The relict of Sir <hi>JOHN READE,</hi> (Sometimes whil'ſt he lived) of <hi>Sorangle</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> Knight.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Edmund Pinchbeck,</hi> B. D.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Bleſſed and holy is he that hath part in the firſt reſurrection, on ſuch the ſecond death hath no power.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Revel. 20.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>With thee it the Well of life, and in thy light ſhall we ſee light.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal, 36.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> &amp; <hi>E. M.</hi> for <hi>Humf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey Tuckey,</hi> at the black-ſpread Eagle in Fleet ſtreet, over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church. 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118106:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118106:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipful THOMAS READE Eſquire, AND M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
               <hi>BRIDGET READE,</hi> his right vertuous wife, eldeſt daughter, and one of the Co-heirs of the Right-Worſhipful Sir <hi>CHARLES CROFTS</hi> of <hi>Bardwell</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> Knight.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od in his providence, and goodneſſe, hath ſo ordered the holy Scriptures, ſo adapt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to all ſorts and conditions of people, ſo fitted them for us, according to our ſeveral wits, our ſeveral capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and apprehenſions, that every one (whoſoever with due and requiſite preparation addreſſes himſelfe to the ſearch of the ſame) may receive benefit by them. Here is ſtrong meat for the beſt ſtomack, and milke for the tendereſt babe; here are depths (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Gregories</hi> reſemblance) where the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant may ſwim, and ſhalloweſt foards where the lamb may wade, without danger of drowning,
<pb facs="tcp:118106:3"/>here are ſome things cloſed, and ſealed up, that a <hi>Daniel</hi> cannot understand, <hi>Dan. 12.8.</hi> ſome thing againe ſo obvious and manifest (like <hi>Habakkuks</hi> viſion) that he that runnes may read. From this extent and fulneſſe of the holy Scriptures, me thinks I hear reſounding that of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, Ho, every one that thirſteth, come to the waters.</hi> If God hath thus prepared them for the general good of all, thus furniſhed them to give ſatisfaction to all the thirſty deſires of our ſoules: is it not equal that every one (without exception) ſhould take notice of them? challenge his intereſt in them? improve them to the intended good of his ſoul? God brooks not our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in them; if God have written unto <hi>Ephraim,</hi> the great things of the Law, and then (ungrateful fair ſuch a favour) if he ſo neglect them that they be counted as ſtrange things, <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſhall hear tell of it, God by way of complaint will charge it againſt him, as you ſee, <hi>Hoſea 8.12.</hi> But now from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the holy Scriptures, you may eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the imperfection of this enſuing Sermon; for although it be derived from the Scriptures, and for the ſubſtance and matter of it, be wholly terminated in the ſame; yet herein it degenerates, and becomes unlike them, in that it affoards no depths for Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants, nor ſtrong meat for ſtronger Chriſtians, no entertainment for men of higher endowments. As
<pb facs="tcp:118106:3"/>
               <hi>Job</hi> brings in the creatures, returning their anſwers concerning the place of wiſdome, <hi>The depth ſaith It is not in me; the ſea ſaith, It is not in me, Job 28.14.</hi> ſo if you ſhould enquire here for theſe arcane, hidden ſublimities, into which Eagle-ey'd ingenuity eſpecially delights to pry, this poore piece would an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer accordingly, that none of theſe myſterious ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties are found within the barren region of theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult lines. And therefore not to prejudice ſharper wits, more exerciſed in the things of God, but to leave them to the height of their wonted ſpeculations, leſt after they have read it over, they finde cauſe to complaine with him in the Comoedy; <hi>Pol ego ole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um &amp; operam perdidi,</hi> I have loſt no leſſe then my time, and labour about it. If it were in my power to make choice of my Readers; I would admit none but ſuch as could diſpenſe with that, which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle calls milk, wholeſome, but common and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary food, and that dreſt up after a plain countrey-faſhion. As for your ſelfe (worthy Sir) to whom in the firſt place it ſtands directed, although there be no Adamant, nothing of worth in it, to attract your acceptance; yet I know you cannot, but affoard it a courteous entertainment, if in theſe reſpects you be pleaſed to reflect upon it; as firſt, how it was preached at the funeral of your dear mother, that honoured La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the Lady <hi>Anne Reade.</hi> Or ſecondly, how (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb facs="tcp:118106:4"/>to your love to the Lord Jeſus) it ſtands impreſt with the image and ſuperſcription of Chriſt, bearing that name in chiefe which is (as <hi>Bernard</hi> exalts it) as honey in the mouth, muſick in the ear, Jubilee in the heart, that name which is all fragrant, and odoriferous, as an oyntment poured forth, <hi>Cant. 1.1.</hi> that ſole and only name, that imports ſalvatton, <hi>Acts 4.12.</hi> Or Laſtly, (being a diſcourſe of that happy life, we derive from our bleſſed Saviour) how it may fortifie and ſtrengthen your hopes againſt that fear, wherein the hope of the wicked faileth, <hi>Prov. 11.7.</hi> even the fear of the King of feares, death. As for the publication of it, had not the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of ſome (whoſe deſires were equivalent to commands, whoſe requeſts brook no denial) over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come mine averſeneſſe, I had never adventured to tender ſuch a poor mite to the publike treaſury, ſuch worthleſſe goats-haire to the ſervice of the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. For (according to the unexpected ſuddenneſſe of the occaſion) as it was haſtily formed, (not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the happineſſe of theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe ſecond reviſing conſiderations (to which all things accurate and polite are beholden;) It was put off in an ordinary vulgar habite, without all requiſite po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh that might make it fit for open view. But now ſith it must abroad to viſit the world, (and I cannot withhold it) not to diſmiſſe it without a benediction,
<pb facs="tcp:118106:4"/>let it go, and proſper; a little ſparke blown up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt drie fewel, ſuch as is apt and fit for combuſtion, eaſily kindles, and breakes forth into a flame, ſo a weake word (if ſtirred up by his Spirit) of whom it was ſaid, <hi>Did not our hearts burn within us, whileſt he talked with us?</hi>) may warme affection, inflame zeal, effect ſomething that is good in an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt heart. If therefore your ſelfe, your vertuous wife, your deſerving ſiſters, Miſtris <hi>Anne Ogle,</hi> Miſtris <hi>Judith Robinſon,</hi> Miſtris <hi>Martha Empſon,</hi> whom I ever honoured for their piety, and goodneſſe, or any other of your faire flouriſhing family, who for the diſeaſed Ladies ſake, may peradventure be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to take notice of it, or any other of Gods people, any where belonging to the houſehold of God, may in the influence of it (the Spirit of God working by it) receive any furtherance in the wayes of God, and hereby gaine any nearer communion with the fountaine of life, our bleſſed Saviour; my deſired end is accompliſhed. Thus with the tender of all unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed reſpect (and herein I cannot but remember him as intereſſed in the ſame) whom mine obliged thoughts ſuffer not to forget, your dear Father in law, Sir <hi>Charles Crofts,</hi> mine honoured friend, together with the very good Lady, the Lady <hi>Crofts,</hi> his prudent, vertuous, and duly reſpected wife;) I ſhall ever pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition the Father of mercies, that your Tabernacle
<pb facs="tcp:118106:5"/>may be peacefull, your cup overflowing, your wayes proſperous, your children gracious, your dayes many, your death comfortable, your ſalvation ſure, and that through him that loved us, and gave himſelfe for us, Chriſt our Lord: To whom be glory for ever, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſervant in the Lord, EDMUND PINCHBECK</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118106:5"/>
            <head>The Fountaine of Life, or Life in its derivation from CHRIST.</head>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 8.35.</hi>
               </bibl> Who ſo findeth me, findeth life.</q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the faithfull devout ſoul admires the beauty and perfection of her beloved, ſets her higheſt eſtimate upon him, makes him her ſole and only glory, and in ſtrong deſires of communion with him, is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed in her affections, that ſhe becomes even ſick of Love, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.5. So ſhe preferres the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him (that excellent knowledge as the Apoſtle cals it, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8.) above all the knowledge in the world, ſhe counts that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge not only her deepeſt learning, but higheſt happineſſe upon earth, even her eternal life, (as Chriſt himſelfe ſtiles it) <hi>John</hi> 17.3. How reſolute the Apoſtle advances this knowledge, unwilling to exchange it for any other, you fee by that in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2. <hi>I determined not to know any thing among you, &amp;c.</hi> The Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans affected learning, many of them addicted themſelves to the ſtudy of arts, and ſciences, and were ſuch good proficients in the ſame, that <hi>Tully</hi> calls Corinth <hi>Lumeu totius Graeciae,</hi> the eye and light of all <hi>Greece:</hi> But what was all this Corinthian learning, (the Apoſtle being Judge) to the glad tidings of ſalvation? what was all their Ethicks, Politicks, their Philoſophical depths, Rhetorical ſtraines, Poetical devices, to that great myſtery of godlineſſe, <hi>God manifeſt in the fleſh?</hi> the Apoſtle ſees ſuch an emptineſſe in mans wiſdome (preciſely conſidered in it ſelfe) that he will not own it, but rejects it as altogether unworthy to ſtand in competition with the deep things of God. As St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes of himſelfe that it abated the heat of his love to <hi>Tullies Hortenſius,</hi> a book whereof he was formerly much enamoured,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118106:6"/>only upon this ground (as himſelfe makes the relation) becauſe in that book the name of Chriſt was not to be found. So for all the people of God, he that hath ever rightly taſted the honey, and honey-comb of Evangelical ſweetneſſe, can never terminate his deſires, never reſt fully ſatisfied in any contentment (how plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to fleſh and blood, or glorious ſoever it be in the eye of the world) that relates not to Chriſt, is not perfumed with the odours of his merits, is not inſcribed with that holy and reverend name Jeſus. Hence it is that the Sunne-clothed woman, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1. (the embleme of the whole Church) is ſaid to have the Moon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her foot, but upon her head a crown of twelve ſtarres; as for the world, (all the inferiour things of this life, which for their inconſtant mutability are as the Moone) ſhe lightly regards: But as for the Doctrine of the Goſpel, (that divine light made known to the world by thoſe great Luminaries, thoſe bright ſhining ſtarres, in the right hand of Chriſt, the twelve Apoſtles) that ſhe prizes as a crowne of glory, that ſhe highly exalts, ſo honours, that all other things are as nothing to her in compariſon of it. And this the ſaints do, not from a precipitate raſhneſſe, but from all deliberation, and advice; <hi>I count all things but loſſe, &amp;c. Phil.</hi> 3.8. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the place before quoted, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2 and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here, are words of cenſure, and judgement, I determined, I count, as if the Apoſtle ſhould ſay, I ſee good reaſon why I ſhould magnifie this knowledge, I have good ground for it, why I ſhould purchaſe it with the loſſe of all things: But why is it ſo deſirable? what do the people of God diſcerne in it, to be ſo inamoured on it? In a word, it only availes <hi>to make wiſe unto ſalvation,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. It was paradventure a raſh cenſure which was put upon <hi>Aristotle,</hi> that great Maſter and Prince of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, <hi>Vae tibi Ariſtoteles, laudaris ubi non es, damnaris ubi es,</hi> Wo to thee <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that art admired where thou art not, but damn'd where thou art. But I wiſh it prove not oft too true amongſt men of higheſt endowments, what <hi>Auſtin</hi> (ſpeaking by <hi>Anthony</hi> the hermite) was once a fraid of, for his own particular, <hi>Indocti rapiunt coelum, &amp;c.</hi> The unlearned take heaven by violence; whileſt we with all our learning, (ſuch learning,) are tumbling down to hell. Yea it matters not what a mans qualifications be; ſuppoſe there were a man (as was ſpoken by one <hi>Berengarius</hi>) that did know all knowables, were wiſer then he that was
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118106:6"/>wiſer then all the children of the Eaſt, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 4. were able to fathom the depths of all ſecrets, comprehend the myſterie of all arts and ſciences; what then? did he not amidſt all theſe his intellectual treaſures, diſcern the unſearchable riches of Chriſt, as the Apoſtle calls them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.8. did he not know him the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of whom is our Juſtification, <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 35.11.) he would ſtill for all this be found to abide in darkneſſe, ſtill to remaine a poore miſerable forlorn man. But why do I make ſuch a preface, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſuch a commendation of this ſuper-excellent evangelical knowledge, but that I might ingratiate my text, and gaine your attention to the ſame; for what is the ſubſtance, and burthen of it, but Chriſt? Chriſt in his relation to the Church, Chriſt as the aime and ſcope of our endeavours, Chriſt as the fountaine of life, the Author of our happineſſe. Now (as the ſtarre did the wiſe men of old) if it bring us into the ſight and viſion of our bleſſed Saviour, deſerves it not to be heeded and obſerved ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly? Oh that it had ſome <hi>Apollos,</hi> ſome golden-mouthed <hi>Chryſostome,</hi> whoſe tongue might be as the pen of a ready wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, every way furniſht to a full diſcovery of the ſame; then (like <hi>Peter</hi> at the transfiguration of Chriſt upon the mount) you would think it good to be here, good through my text (like that grate or lattice the ſpouſe ſpeaks of, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.9.) to behold him that is ſo faire, and ruddy, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10. fairer then then ſonnes of men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.2. even the expreſſe image and brightneſſe of his Fathers glory, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. Now for the anſwerable correſpondency it beares to the preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>In times of heavineſſe, and dejection, when the heart is perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and troubled, when the ſould, (to ſpeake in <hi>Jeremies</hi> phraſe) is fill'd with bitterneſſe, and made drunk with worme-wood, what more ſeaſonable then words of comfort and conſolation? according to that of <hi>Solomon, Heavineſſe in the heart of man maketh it ſtoop, but a good word maketh it glad, Prov.</hi> 12.25. Now for funeral heavineſſe, when the mourners go abroad in the ſtreets, for ſuch ſorrows as theſe that ſo deeply afflict us for the preſent, what words more comfortable, more cordial, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhful, then a doctrine of life? of ſuch a life as knows no death, as triumphs over death; as can expoſtulate with death, in the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? O hell, where is thy victory?</hi> ſuch a life there is to be had in Chriſt, and ſuch a life my
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118106:7"/>my text tenders, <hi>(He that findeth me, findeth life.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The intent and ſcope of my text, is to impreſſe upon us the knowledge of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the argument is from the utility, and benefit of it; that which brings an happy and bleſſed life, the life of grace here, and the life of glory hereafter, ſuch a life as my text ſpeaks of, deſerves by all meanes poſſible with all intention, and diligence, to be ſought after, and inquired into; but ſuch is the Lord Jevus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>In the words you have firſt the fountaine of our happineſſe, <hi>Me</hi>]</p>
            <p>Secondly the benefit derived from the ſame, and that's <hi>Life</hi>]</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the imployment of a Chriſtian about theſe bleſſed ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and thats <hi>finding</hi>]</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the party intereſſed in the ſame, and that is ſet down indefinitely, and without limitation, <hi>who</hi>] That is any one, of what eſtate and condition ſoeve he be. For the firſt,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whoſo findeth me</hi>] <hi>Me?</hi> who is it that makes us ſo happy, and bleſſed; if found by us? The holy Spirit deſcribes him by diverſe characters, and properties, in the precedent verſes; as firſt by his name, and title, and that is wiſdome: the Hebrew word, in <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.20. and <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.1. and ſo in ſome other places of this book, is found in the plural number, to note that this wiſdome is the perfection of wiſdome; him <hi>in whom all the treaſures of wiſdome, and knowledge are hid,</hi> as the Apoſtle deſcribes him. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.3. Secondly by his zeal, that he beares to the good of the ſonnes of men, this wiſdome ſtands, and calls, and cryes, and puts forth her voice, (there's her importunity) by the wayes, places of the paths, tops of the high places, the gates, entry into the city, the coming in of the doores (there's her vigilancy, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection, laying hold of opportunities) and why doth wiſdome take all this paines? the end ſhe aimeth at is, to make us ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally wiſe, becauſe we are ſimple and fooliſh ſhe would have us to underſtand wiſdome, and be of an underſtanding heart, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.2, 3, 4, 5. Thirdly from the excellency of her doctrine, <hi>Give eare and I will ſpeak<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</hi> verſe 6. There may be frowardneſſe, perverſeneſſe, wickedneſſe in the doctrine of men, but there's nothing but verity, truth, ſincerity, righteouſneſſe in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt; the doctrines of men may be vaine, fruitleſſe, but this is of higheſt concernment; do you tell of ſilver, and gold, &amp;c?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118106:7"/>all things thou canſt deſire are not to be compared to her; from the 6 verſe to the 12. Fourthly, from her effects, and conſequents, where wiſdome is, there is prudence, counſel, ſtrength, exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, preferment, ſupport of thrones, decrees of juſtice, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, holineſſe, riches, durable riches, honour; from the 12. <hi>verſe</hi> to the 22. Fifthly, from he eternity, before his works of old, depths, fountaines, hills, mountaines, heavens, clouds, &amp;c. from <hi>verſe</hi> 22. to the 30. Sixtly, from Gods delight and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency in her, I was brought up with him, &amp;c. <hi>verſe</hi> 30. Laſtly, from the delight this wiſdome takes amongſt the ſonnes of men, <hi>verſe</hi> 31. From all which in the union of them, you may gather what Majeſty, reſides in the words of my text, here's no leſſe then perfection it ſelfe, the uncreated wiſdome of God, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. From when we may note the all-ſufficiency of our bleſſed Saviour.</p>
            <p>¶ How the Lord Jeſus, the Lord of life, whom we profeſſe, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom we depend for ſalvation, is a Saviour every way furniſht for the accompliſhment of our happineſſe.</p>
            <p>He that hath ſuch wiſdome, zeal, doctrine, endowments, eternity, acceptance with God, love to the ſonnes of men, muſt needs prevaile in what he undertakes. How Chriſt is qualified for the ſalvation of his people, you may gather by that in <hi>Col.</hi> 1.19. <hi>It pleaſed the Father that in him ſhould all fulneſſe dwell;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, fulneſſe in the latitude of it, to pardon ſinne, heal infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſanctifie corrupt natures, infuſe ſpiritual endowments; juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ſinners, conferre everlaſting happineſſe, are high works, the leaſt of them argues of ſtock of infinite mercy, infinite grace, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite holineſſe, infinite righteouſneſſe: now for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all theſe, here was all fulneſſe; here was no gift, no grace, no requiſite abilities withheld from him; no, here was the fulneſſe of the Godhead bodily, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.9. yea what Chriſt was you ſee by the ſtile, and titles the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> gives, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 9.6. <hi>wonderful counſellour, mighty God, everlaſting Father, &amp;c.</hi> are we loſt in <hi>Adam,</hi> he's wonderful to reſtore us, wonderful that is <hi>ſupra humanum captum,</hi> above mans thought or apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his power; are we deſtitute of heavenly wiſdome? have we not the knowledge of holy things? he's the counſellour to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118106:8"/>adviſe are, we infirme and weak, to withſtand the ſpiritual ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our ſoules? he is the mighty God, to ſave us; are we poor and indigent? he is an everlaſting Father, to provide for us; are we liable to afflictions, and troubles? he is the Prince of peace, to quiet us, not only to ſpeak peace, but to command peace to our ſoules. To this purpoſe how full and effectual is that deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption which the ſame Prophet makes of Chriſt as he ſtands in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the Church, as the ſpiritual houſe and building of God; <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 8.16. <hi>Bebold, I lay in Sion for a foundation, a ſtone, a try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtone, a precious corner-ſtone, a ſure foundation, &amp;c.</hi> As for the meaning of the words, in general, the Prophet intimates, and that from God himſelfe what a bleſſing God had ordeined in Chriſt, for the good of the Church; what a good foundation is to the ſtructure, and building erect upon it, ſuch is Chriſt to the ſpiritual <hi>Sion,</hi> ſo he ſupports her, ſo upholds her, ſo beares her up, that the believer rightly founded upon him, ſhall not make haſte in a deſperate, comfortleſſe way, as if he were flying from the face of a purſuing, prevailing, deſtroying enemy, where there were no help, none to deliver; ſo the Apoſtles render it, <hi>He ſhall not be aſhamed</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 9. <hi>ult. He ſhall not be confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6 And what a benefit this is, the Prophet ſhews by the note of attention he ſets upon it, <hi>Behold, I lay;</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, This is no ordinary common worke, but of higheſt conſequence and concernment: Now for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, and better expreſſion of this reſemblance, the Prophet delivers himſelfe with variety of choice words, adding one meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorical terme to another, for the deeper impreſſion whereof it will not be loſt labour (I ſuppoſe) eſpecially conſidering they all tend to the point in hand, to examine each particular by it ſelf; The firſt we meet with, is a foundation-ſtone, <hi>Behold I lay in Sion for a foundation, a ſtone;</hi> a ſtone in the holy Scripture is a frequent embleme of Chriſt, and it implies many myſteries; <hi>Daniel</hi> calls him, <hi>a ſtone cut out of the mountaines, without hands, Dan.</hi> 2.45. there's his divine nature, together with his ordination, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from God. <hi>Zachary,</hi> a carved ſtone, therein you may read his ſufferings. The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, a stumbling ſtone, and a rock of offence, Iſaiah</hi> 8.14. There you have his judgements upon the wicked. <hi>Zachary</hi> again in the ſame place, <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.9. calls him <hi>a ſtone with ſeven eyes,</hi> that may note his omniſcience, together
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118106:8"/>with that light, and knowledge imparted to his Saints. <hi>Peter a loving ſtone,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1 4. To ſhew how he lives in himſelf, and gives life to others; here in this place a foundation ſtone, to give us to underſtand how the Church is founded and built, how ſhe reſts and depends upon him. Secondly, he is ſaid to be a tryed ſtone: afflictions are the trials of ſtrength; <hi>If thou fainteſt in the day of adverſity, thy ſtrength is ſmall, Prov.</hi> 24.10. Now what was the life or Chriſt, but a tragedy of afflictions from his nativity till his reſurrection, yet (bleſſed be God for it) this ſtone crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled not, budged not out of his place. <hi>He came leaping by the mountaines, and skipping by the hills.</hi> By mountaines ſome under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his greater miſeries, by hills his leſſer afflictions; by his leaping and skipping, his alacrity and chearfulneſſe in embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the ſame. Thirdly, as he's a tryed ſtone, ſo a precious corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone; a corner-ſtone, <hi>quia utrumque parietem conjungit,</hi> becauſe he conjoynes the ſeveral ſides of the Church into one. Here men and Angels, Jewes and Gentiles, ſaints in heaven and earth, men of all Countreys and conditions, meet in Chriſt, and in him grow up into an holy temple in the Lord. And how precious he is, may appear from the gifts and graces he beſtows upon us. <hi>He became poor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſaies the Apoſtle, <hi>that we through his poverty might be made rich,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.9. how rich theſe ſpiritual bleſſings make us, you may gather by that high commendation, that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſets upon wiſdome, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.14, 15. <hi>Her merchandize is better then ſilver, and her gain better then gold, &amp;c.</hi> As for ſilver and gold, they have that credit in the world, finde that general acceptance, that I deeme it ſuperfluous; (every one being ſo well conceited of them) to ſpeak a word in their behalfe; Oh how do the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous ſonnes of men adore this Sunne, and Moon, as <hi>Job</hi> calls them, <hi>Job</hi> 31.26. How do they preferre this <hi>thick clay,</hi> this red and white earth; thoſe lumpiſh Idols before the <hi>ſtrong God of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation?</hi> for the gaining of theſe how deſparately do they hazard the loſing of their deareſt ſoules? the dammage whereof the whole world cannot recompence, <hi>Mark</hi> 8.35. In a word, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (neither to abaſe them, nor ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e them after the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weening imagination of the world) they are in themſelves the good bleſſings of God upon us; God ſeeth them requiſite for us, and therefore doth promiſe the poſſeſſion of them to his deareſt ſervants. <hi>Job</hi> 22.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Thou ſhalt lay up gold as duſt, &amp;c.</hi> But now
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118106:9"/>this wiſdome, this holy and ſpiritual wiſdome, whoſe birth and pedegree is from above, <hi>Job.</hi> 32.8. whoſe demeanour, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in the world is <hi>pure, peaceable, gentle, &amp;c. James</hi> 2.17. whoſe imployment is <hi>to fear God, and keep his commandements, Job</hi> 28.28. whoſe recompence to her entertainers is <hi>life, and peace, Rom.</hi> 8.6. ſhe doth not only tranſcend the worth of gold, and ſilver, but all things elſe however valued; ſhe is <hi>more precious then Rubies, &amp;c.</hi> There is no precious pearle, but hath ſome egregious vertue, as <hi>Cardan</hi> the great ſearcher of nature affirmes, and ſo experience teſtifies; ſome are ſovereigne againſt the ſadneſſe, and feares of melancholy, as the <hi>Topaz;</hi> ſome againſt leproſie; others againſt poiſon, as the <hi>Saphir;</hi> others quell the intemperate drunken diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the braine, as the <hi>Amethiſt:</hi> and as they are vertuous in their operations, ſo opinion hath rated them accordingly; I need not inſtance in the great price of <hi>Cleopatrae's</hi> pearle, ſhe diſſolved and drunk in an health to <hi>Mark Athony,</hi> or others according to the relation of hiſtory, the teſtimony of <hi>Pliny</hi> may ſave that labour, <hi>Culmen principiúmque omnium rerum pretii margaritae te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent,</hi> of all precious things in the world, <hi>Margarites</hi> are in high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt eſtimate and account; not much inferiour to which (as of all others moſt lightſome, and glorious,) is the <hi>Rubie</hi> (or <hi>Carbuncle</hi> as <hi>Junius, Tremelius, Buxtorphius</hi> and others read it;) yet all theſe precious things muſt ſubmit and ſtoop to this wiſdome; yea as if all this were not enough, <hi>Solomon</hi> challenges the very wiſhes, &amp; deſires of our hearts; our hearts can deſire golden mountaines, <hi>ens</hi> and <hi>non ens,</hi> thouſands of Rammes, ten thouſand rivers of oile; yet <hi>omnes volunt ates tuae</hi> according to the Hebrew theſe very voli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and wiſhes of thy ſoul (in all thoſe glorious objects, they aime at) fall beneath the height of this wiſdome, nor all things thou canſt deſire. Now from hence argue, If one particular grace be ſo precious, what are all theſe ſpiritual treaſures, in the whole liſt, and traine of them together? and if there be ſuch a tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent excellency in them, what is there in him, from whoſe fulneſſe they are all derived; yea he is not only the fountain of all grace, but of glory too, and therefore muſt needs be precious indeed. Laſtly, he is a ſure foundation, there are divers foundations men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the ſcriptures; Kings and Princes are foundations, ſo the Pſalmiſt ſtiles them, <hi>All the foundations of the earth are out of courſe, Pſal.</hi> 82.5. ſo the doctrine of the Apoſtles, <hi>Epheſi.</hi> 2.20. the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgement
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118106:9"/>of the doctrine of faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. But Chriſt is <hi>fundamentum fundamentorum,</hi> the firſt and original foundation, upon whom all others depend; and for his ſtability and ſureneſſe, he is Alpha and Omega, the firſt and the laſt, the beginning and end, one that never alters, never changes, yeſterday and to day, and the ſame for ever. Now what do theſe and the like deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions of our bleſſed Saviour import, but his perfection for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of our happineſſe, how he is every way furniſh't to ſatisfie Gods juſtice in our behalfe, and to gaine acceptance with God for us? yea the reſult of theſe, and the like places, can be no leſſe then this, that Chriſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Zachary</hi> in his hymne ſtiles him, the horn and ſtrength of ſalvation, a mighty powerful ſalvation for us.</p>
            <p>From whence in the firſt place, you may ſtand and wonder at the ſtupendious folly of the ſonnes of men, that refuſe (like ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate <hi>Jeruſalem, Matth</hi> 23.37.) to be gathered under the all-foſtring wings of his eſpecial goodneſſe and grace, that (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all his paines about them, all his gracious treaties with them, for the good of their ſoules,) will not be perſwaded to know the things that belong unto their peace; <hi>He came unto his own, but his own received him not, John</hi> 1.11. No, inſtead of due acknowledgement and reſpect, they hid their faces from him, and eſteemed him not, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. ſo the Jewes dealt with him of old, and what better acceptance doth he finde amongſt us Chriſtians for the preſent? we have had a day, a faire &amp; outſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed day of grace, wherein the Lord Jeſus for a long time toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath ſtood knocking at the doores of our hearts; proffering himſelfe with all importunity, but who hath opened to his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment? no, have not we oppoſed his government by the rebellion of our luſts? his truth by the blindneſſe of our errours? his unity by the faction of our ſchiſmes? his worſhip by the athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtical profaneneſſe of our indevotion? his holineſſe by the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of our lives, and converſations? yea, may not God as juſtly complaine againſt us, (eſpecially conſidering what clearer light, what more effectuall meanes of grace we have enjoyed,) as ever againſt <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, as you have it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>ult. All the day long have I ſtretched out mine hand to a diſobedient, gain-ſaying people.</hi> But now conſider here for thine own particular, in this thine averſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from him, what a traitor art thou to thine own ſoul? ſay,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118106:10"/>art thou athirſt? he is an everflowing fountaine: art thou hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry? he is the bread of life: art thou naked? he's the robe of righteouſneſſe: art thou afflicted? he's a hiding place from the ſtorme, a refuge from the tempeſt: art thou ſpiritually ſick? he's the Phyſician of our ſoules: art thou liable to the wrath to come? he's thine attonement: in a word he is unto us all, and in all, <hi>Col</hi> 3.11. Oh therefore, why art thou ſo cruel to thy ſelf as to neglect ſo great ſalvation? what is a broken ciſterne to a fountain of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving water? the hungry prodigall deſired huskes, to the liberal plenty of his fathers houſe: ſo what are weak, empty, fading crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-comforts, to the full, permanent, ſoule-reviving refreſhments of thy Saviour? We count it weakneſſe and folly in the poore In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians that they ſell their gold, pearle, richeſt comodities, for glaſſe, knives, iron, inferiour trifles; but oh that we were ſenſible of our own madneſſe in exchanging (like <hi>Eſau's</hi> birth-right, for a meſſe of pottage) the ineſtimable treaſures of our happineſſe, for the traſh, inconſiderable, lying vanities of the world.</p>
            <p>Secondly, here's a ſpring of abundant comfort, and conſolation to believers; what feares? what doubts? what perplexities can now poſſeſſe thy ſoul? or rather what boldneſſe and confidence towards God canſt thou want? if Chriſt be ſo accompliſht for thine happineſſe; who then (according to the triumphant chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge of the Apoſtle in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.) can be againſt us? can condemn us? can lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect? can ſeparate from his love? To inſtance in particular, what is that that doth perplex and trouble thee? haſt thou forgotten thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth? and doth thine offended conſcience now condemning, write bitter things againſt thee? why in the blood of Chriſt, <hi>here's a fountaine opened for ſin, and foruncleanneſſe, Zach.</hi> 13.1. like leprous <hi>Naaman</hi> in <hi>Jordan</hi> could we here waſh our pollut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſoules, the leproſie of our ſinnes (how filthy and impure ſoever) would be cured, and done away, or in the ſecond place, art thou diſmayed in thy thoughts, and apprehenſions at the rigour of Gods juſtice? doth thy fleſh (like <hi>Davids</hi>) tremble becauſe of him, and art thou a fraid of his judgements? Behold, there is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation made in the blood of the Croſſe ſuch a reconciliation as ſhall make thee holy, and unblameable, and without fault in his ſight, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.22. It was an argument of comfort to <hi>Manoahs</hi> wife the mother of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> that God would not kill her, nor her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118106:10"/>becauſe he had received an offering from them, <hi>Judg.</hi> 13.23. why God hath not only received an offering from thee, <hi>a ſacrifice of a ſweet ſmelling ſavour to God, Epheſ.</hi> 5.2. but likewiſe (like the Ramme that was ſacrificed for <hi>Iſaac</hi>) prepared it for thee, and that from all eternity. Or in the third place, art thou afraid of poverty, and want, that God will ſtraiten thee in his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward mercies, the things of this life, why if he have given thee Chriſt, (as the Apoſtle argues, <hi>a majori ad minus, Rom</hi> 8.32.) what will he withhold from thee? <hi>will he not with him give us all things alſo?</hi> Or 4ly, art thou afraid of alteration, and change in thy condition? leſt the extremity and violence of afflictions, troubles, temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould drive thee from God, and conſequently from thine expected happ neſſe: why, Chriſt is a Rock, if thou beeſt ſounded on him, he'l hold thee up from falling, ſo that neither windes nor raine, nor floods, no diſturbing oppoſitions how malignant ſoever, ſhall ever ſupplant thee, overturn thee from thy ſtation. In a word, if we be his, he will be ours according to all the relations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we draw nigh unto him; Are we his vineyard? he will fence us about with the hedge and wall of his providence, ordering us with all requiſite husbandry for fertility and fruitfulneſſe, <hi>Eſaiah</hi> 5.2. Are we his ſheep? he will be our ſhepherd to feed us, and fold us in a good paſture upon the high mountaines of <hi>Iſrael</hi> by the rivers, <hi>Ezeck.</hi> 34.13, 14. Are we his temple? he will be graciouſly preſent with us, even dwelling amongſt us, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. Are we his ſpouſe? he will take pleaſure in our beauty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.11. Are we his body? (in an holy union with us, to direct and guide us in our wayes, to order our affaires for us, to ſupply us, with the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his ſpirit) he is our head, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.18. yea according to his proprieties in us, he will accommodate himſelf to our ſeveral ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, and wants: And to this purpoſe all his attributes are at work for us. In his ſtrength <hi>he will ſubdue our iniquities</hi> (Micha. 7.19.) In his patience <hi>he will ſpare us as a man ſpareth his own ſonne, that ſerveth him,</hi> Malach. 3.17. In his mercy and wiſdome <hi>he will correct us in meaſure, and not leave us altogether unpuniſhed, Jer.</hi> 30.11. In his pitty and compaſſion he will <hi>preach glad tidings to the poore, binde up the broken-hearted. Iſaiah</hi> 61.1. Laſtly, in his free and deſerved goodneſſe, <hi>his rich grace,</hi> as the Apoſtle calls it, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.7. (becauſe this world is a <hi>Baca, a valley of tears,</hi> a ſea of glaſſe mingled with fire) <hi>he is gone to prepare a place for us, John</hi> 14.2. even thoſe eternal manſions in heaven.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118106:11"/>
            <p>Thirdly, it ſhewes where to found and ſettle our hopes, all our confidence, all our expectation in the wayes of happineſſe. The Apoſtle tells the Epheſians that they were <hi>without hope,</hi> that is, ſolid and ſubſtantial hope, and he gives the reaſon for it, in the beginning of that verſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. becauſe that all that time they were <hi>without Chriſt. Chriſtus eſt omnium promiſſionum fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp; ſpei</hi> (ſays <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the place.) All the promiſes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently all hope is founded on Chriſt, and therefore as they were without him, ſo they muſt needs be without hope. When the Emperour <hi>Nicephorus Phocas</hi> for his ſecurity had built a mighty wall about his palace, it's related how he heard in the night, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>voice ſaying, O King, though thou build as high as the clouds, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; yet the city will be eaſily taken, the ſin within will marre all. I may apply it to all the Idolatrous ſons of men, that make fleſh their arme, and withdraw their hearts from the Lord; tell me, what forts, what caſtles, what ſtrong holds doſt thou erect and build unto thy ſelfe? As <hi>Pharaoh</hi> had his chariots, <hi>Aſa</hi> his Phyſicians, <hi>Jonah</hi> his ſhip for <hi>Tarſhiſh, Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib</hi> his army, <hi>Iſrael</hi> his reſt and dependance upon <hi>Egypt:</hi> ſo every natural heart, hath ſomething either in her ſelfe; or the creature, to betake her ſelfe unto, but how faire and promiſing thoſe objects of our hopes be, it matters not, they (as the Lord ſpeakes, by the ſtrength of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and ſhadow of <hi>Egypt, Iſaiah</hi> 30.3.) ſhall be your ſhame and your confuſion; yea, whileſt ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity takes up her habitation in thine heart, thou ſhalt not proſper. As <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeakes by riches, <hi>that they avail not in the day of wrath:</hi> ſo you may ſay of all thoſe glorious idols of the ſonnes of men, they are all as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> chariot-wheeles, that fell off when he had the moſt ſervice for them, or as the walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> that fell down when the enemy was neareſt to enter, or as the brooks that <hi>Job</hi> ſpeakes of (<hi>Job</hi> 6.19.) that were then exhauſt and dryed up, when the troopes of <hi>Tema,</hi> and the companies of <hi>Sheba</hi> were the moſt afflicted with thirſt, and ſtood in the greateſt expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them. And as this appears through the various paſſages of our liver, ſo ever in the approach of death; as death is the King of feares, and of all terrible things the moſt formidable, ſo that ſoul muſt needs be in an happy condition, that is then throughly furniſhed with well-grounded comforts, when it invades. But alas, the hope of the wicked (it matters not what the wicked man was
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118106:11"/>how great, how glorious in the eyes of the world, nor what his hope were, how preſumptuous) all then fades and failes, bequeath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the miſerable ſoul to utter and endleſſe deſperation, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.7. And therefore diſclaiming all other dependancies, let us betake our ſelves to him that is the hope of our glory, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. this hope will never make thee aſhamed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5. no, this hope will abide with thee in the evil day, will call unto thee in the time of affliction (like the angel to <hi>Hagar</hi> in the wilderneſſe) and ſay, Fear not. In the time of trouble it will preſent thee with more fiery centinels for thy protection, then <hi>Eliſha's</hi> ſervant once ſaw about beleag uered <hi>Dothan,</hi> yea, it will gve thee ſongs in the night, enlarge thine heart with joy, and gladneſſe, though with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> thou beeſt in a dungeon.</p>
            <p>And thus we come to the ſecond particular in my text, the Prerogative derived from him, and that is <hi>Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that findeth me]</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>invenit vitas,</hi> not life; but lives in the plural number, to intimate peradventure that life in the whole current of it, in all its qualifications, and reſpects is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from him, and depends upon him; as he is the original of life, <hi>giving life to the world, John</hi> 6.33. ſo he is the ſupporter of it too, it is he that upholds all things by the word of his power, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. All things were created for him, and by him, ſo in him all things conſiſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.17. and hence it is, that in the 30. verſe of this chapter he is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>nutritius,</hi> nouriſher, a foſter-father, one that carefully and faithfully looks to the creature, to preſerve and maintain them in their being, and therefore, if we diſcern any excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in life, apprehend any comfort, take any content in it, let it (with all thankfulneſſe) be aſcribed to his praiſe, yea, as we live in him, ſo (in our ſouls and bodies, and all the parts and faculties of them both) let us live to him, and to the glory of his name. Now according to the latitude of it, we may conſider of life; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as it is in <hi>via,</hi> in this world; or as it is in <hi>Patria,</hi> in the world to come; as it is in this world it runnes in a double channel; Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Grace. The life of nature ſince the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> (ſtrictly and preciſely conſidered in it ſelfe) is but a poor miſerable life; it's incident to the unregenerate, to them that be ſtrangers from the life of God, importing no further happineſſe, then that of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118106:12"/>brute beaſt, the vanity of it appeares; Firſt, in the brevity of it, what's a vapour, a ſhadow, a flower, a dream? things of no ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, no duration; ſuch is life, had we as much happineſſe in our lives, as miſeries; yet was not that happineſſe in reſpect of the brevity of our lives to be reſted upon. Secondly, in reſpect of the difficulty of its ſupport. O what a deal of labour is it to live in this world! what riſing early, going to bed late, eating the bread of carefulneſſe? a heavy burthen in this reſpect is laid upon all the ſonnes of men. Thirdly, in reſpect of the ſinfulneſſe of it; who knowes how oft he offendeth? no, the height and multitude of our ſinnes exceed imagination: Now if every ſin be an oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Gods will, a violation of Gods law, a diſhonour to his name, a ſcandal to his ſaints, the hazard of our ſoules, what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, what content can we expect from ſuch a ſtained, polluted life? Fourthly, from the miſeries of it, <hi>Man that is born of a woman, &amp;c. Job.</hi> 14.1. Brevity of dayes, and plenitude of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry go together, and therefore let us not terminate our deſires in ſuch a life as this, that conſiſts only in the conjunction of ſoul and body; but endeavour the attainment of that holy, ſpiritual, ſupernatural life, the life of grace that conſiſts in the union, and communion of Chriſt and the ſoul; of this life the Apoſtle ſpeakes of, <hi>Gal</hi> 2.20. <hi>I am crucified with Chriſt; nevertheleſſe, I live, &amp;c.</hi> Here was not only a living in the fleſh; but by faith, a living with Chriſt, and this is an happy, and deſircable life indeed, it carries the bleſſing of God along with it, and howſoever it mee s with much oppoſition, many temptations in this world, yet in concluſion it leades to an happy end, according to that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Mark the upright man, and behold the juſt &amp;c.</hi> for the diſcovery of this life, let us obſerve it firſt in the ſeveral degrees and heights of it, and then in its derivation from Chriſt. For the firſt, you may note in the firſt place, the life of righteouſneſſe; <hi>There is none righteous, no not one, Rom.</hi> 3.10. no none in the ſtate of nature. But what are we when we have put on Chriſt? the Apoſtle tells us in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>ult. He that knew no ſinne, was made ſinne for us, &amp;c. the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of God, &amp;c.</hi> not righteous in the concrete, but righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in the abſtract; to note the perfection of that righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe we have in Chriſt; that it is ſuch a righteouſneſſe, as God expects, and requires from us; the receipt of this righteouſneſſe from Chriſt, all believers are bound to acknowledge, <hi>Jer</hi> 23.6
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118106:12"/>This is the name whereby he ſhall be called, <hi>The Lord our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</hi> This is the righteouſneſſe in which the ſaints ſo triumph, <hi>I will greatly rejoyce, &amp;c. Iſaiah</hi> 61.10. yea, if Chriſt be ſuch a righteouſneſſe for us, who can but rejoyce? for then are we free from the malediction and curſe of the law, yea here is not only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an happy and bleſſed redemption from the bondage of the law, from the captivity of ſinne and Satan; but likewiſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, power to be called the ſornes of God; yea here is a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed right and intereſt in the purchaſed poſſeſſion. The ſecond is the life of holineſſe, he is not only wiſdome, righteouſneſſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, but ſanctification too, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. Chriſt doth not only caſt our ſins into the bottome of the ſea, paſſe an act of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion upon them; but ſubdue them, <hi>Micha.</hi> 7.19. not only par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don ſinne, but heale infirmities, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.3. not only free us from the power of ſinne, and of death, but enable us to walk in the Spirit, furniſh us with all requiſite graces, put his Spirit in us, and cauſe us to keep his commandements, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. yea, he that walks not with God in the way of holineſſe, knowes not Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 14.15. Thirdly, of comfort and conſolation; <hi>Behold, I bring you tidings of great joy, &amp;c.</hi> where is joy great, univerſal, &amp;c? why, Chriſt is the ground of it, <hi>This day there is a Saviour born, &amp;c.</hi> yea, as Chriſt is a Saviour, ſo he that experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally knowes him ſo to be, cannot but rejoyce in him, as in the inſtance of the virgin <hi>Mary, My ſoul doth magnifie the Lord, and my ſpirit hath, &amp;c.</hi> yea hence is ſuch a joy the ſtranger meddles not with, a joy unſpeakable and glorious, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. ſuch a joy as the ſaints cannot conteine within themſelves, <hi>They ſhall ſing for joy of heart, Iſaiah</hi> 65.14. <hi>and therefore be glad, O ye righteous, and rejoyce in the Lord, be joyful, &amp;c.</hi> As it is a priviledge, ſo a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty too: now how doth Chriſt effect all this in the hearts of his people? the meanes whereby he works the ſame, are eſpecially theſe two. Firſt, the outward Miniſtery of the word, and then the inward operation of his Spirit. For the firſt, conſider that in <hi>John</hi> 5.25. <hi>The dead ſhall hear the voice of the Sonne of God, and they that hear it ſhall live.</hi> The dead? who are they? the Atheiſt, the Infidel, the drunkard, the wanton, &amp;c. are all dead? <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1. yea, like loathſome carrions they are moſt odious and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the eyes of God, and man; but what? is there for them no poſſibility of life? yes; if they hear and receive the Goſpel,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118106:13"/>they ſhall live: you ſee how hearing and living go together; this ſhould countenance and gaine credit to the word, if thou wouldſt live, heare. As for the ſecond, the Spirit quickens the immortal ſeed of the word, unites unto Chriſt, efformes to the image of God in holineſſe, repleniſhes the heart with good motions, and therefore called <hi>a quickening Spirit, John</hi> 6.63. <hi>the Spirit of life, Rom.</hi> 8.2. and therefore as thou tendereſt life, take heed how thou quencheſt, grieveſt, reſiſteſt the ſame, how both theſe conjoyne and work together to the production of this ſpiritual life, we may illuſtrate from the parable of the drie bones, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. The pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable (properly, and in the firſt place) belongs to the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> upon their return and reſtitution from the land of their captivity; but by ſimilitude and reſemblance (as ſome learned divines have led me in the way) you may ſee the whole ſtate of the Church prefigured in the ſame: in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> you have the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the goſpel; in the drie bones, the ſonnes of men, all dry, and barren, and deſtitute of all ſpiritual goodneſſe; in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying upon theſe drie bones the diſpenſation of the Goſpel, when thoſe Embaſſadours of Chriſt go abroad in the world, they know not whether ſuch and ſuch enormous ſinners may live: if any ask the queſtion, they would with <hi>Ezekiel</hi> referre it to God, <hi>Lord, thou knoweſt,</hi> yet becauſe God ſends them, they go and propheſie accordingly, <hi>O ye drie bones heare the word of the Lord:</hi> and then what follows? behold, in the firſt place a noiſe, and a ſhaking, trouble of conſcience, and perplexity of ſpirit, from the ſenſe of ſinne, and terrour of the Law, as in St. <hi>Peters</hi> converts <hi>that were pricked in their hearts, Acts</hi> 2.37. Then in the ſecond place, you have a meeting of bones, bone unto his bone, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, will, memory, affections, &amp;c. that were formerly ſcattered, and diſperſ't in the wayes of ſinne, all now unite and conſpire together to be a new creature in Chriſt Jeſus. In the third place, <hi>fleſh and ſinews grow upon them, and the skin covers them;</hi> fleſh, that may ſtand for ſoftneſſe of heart, and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of conſcience; ſinews, for ſtrength of reſolution; and the skin, for boldneſſe of profeſſion. And then for the perfection, and conſummation of the new creature, the winde breaths upon it, that is, the holy Spirit, (that winde that blows where it liſteth) furniſhes the ſame with ſaving gifts and graces, and then it lives (a ſpiritual life,) ſtands up upon his feet (to runne the wayes of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118106:13"/>Gods commandements) and becomes a very great army (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared and ready, and enabled to fight the Lords battels) from all which together ye may note in the firſt place, that it is not impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for the worſt of ſinners to be converted, dry bones may live. Secondly, the energie and activity of Gods holy ordinances, as they are from him, and tend to the glory of his name, ſo his power goes along with them, they work wonders, when his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is upon them. Laſtly, what an alteration &amp; change Chriſtianity, and Religion makes, where it is embraced, it turns a valley of dry bones into an army of ſpiritual ſouldiers, fighting under the banner of Chriſt the Captain of their ſalvation. And thus we come to the laſt particular, Life in its perfection, the life of glory;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that heareth my words, and beleeveth in him that ſent me, hath everlasting life, Iohn</hi> 5.24. The glory of this life tranſcends all humane apprehenſion: all the powers and faculties of nature, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain not the ſublimity of it: the eye in ſeeing, eare in hearing, heart in conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ving, extend farre, but here they are all at a <hi>non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus,</hi> all poor deficient; <hi>The thing which eye hath not ſeen, ear not heard, &amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 2.9. and therefore to content our ſelves with a ſhort glimps of it, we may gueſſe at the perfection of it, from theſe and the like grounds, as firſt from the place where this life is led, and that's the Kingdome of God, the paradiſe of God, the houſe of God, the Heaven of Heavens, the city of the living God. St. <hi>Iohn</hi> in the deſcription of this new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> tells us of gold, and pearle, and precious ſtones, there was the Emerauld, Jaſper, Saphir, Berd, Tophas, things of higheſt eſtimate and price, but how farre doth he extend theſe precious things? why, by theſe he only ſets out the glory of the walls, gates, pavements of the ſame, as for the inward furniture, the delights, pleaſures, ſtate, glory, priviledges, prerogatives of the bleſſed citizens, he makes no reſemblance; no, all the precious things in nature, are not worthy to be tender'd for a ſhadow to that ſubſtance. <hi>Glorious things are ſpoken of thee, O thou City of God,</hi> if God hath formed ſo many glorious things for the creatures, why then, that which he hath formed for himſelfe, for his own proper reſidence, and manſion, that muſt needs be compleated with ſurpaſſing glory indeed. Now to be admitted as a citizen to live in ſuch a place, muſt needs be a priviledge of higheſt comfort. Secondly, from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118106:14"/>the glory of the inhabitants in whoſe communion we enjoy the ſame. Now who theſe are the Apoſtle tells in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22. <hi>You are come to mount Sion, &amp;c.</hi> there's the place, the reſident Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants follow, <hi>the company of innumerable Angels, the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the firſt-born, &amp;c.</hi> It's related of <hi>Cato</hi> an old grave Roman, that he adviſed in the purchaſe of a farme or the like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, that a man ſhould conſider of the vicinity or neighbour-hood there, <hi>Ne malum vicinum haberet,</hi> and to that purpoſe they relate the proclamation of <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> a famous Athenian cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in the ſaile of his lands, that if any man would deal with him, he ſhould be ſure of a good neighbour. Beloved, there is a miſerable neighbour-hood in hell, none but wretched ſinners, impure ſpirits, torturing and tormenting devils; Oh take heed, leſt by your ſinnes, and tranſgreſſions, you purchaſe that land of darkneſſe, to your everlaſting confuſion. But now in heaven, O what a glorious, what a bleſſed ſociety is there; for firſt of all, there is God himſelfe, what a communion we have with him you may gather by that petition of our bleſſed Saviour in. <hi>John</hi> 17.21. <hi>I pray, &amp;c. that they all may be one, as thou Father art in me, and I in thee; even that they alſo may be in us,</hi> there is not only a commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion amongſt themſelves, but with God too; O what an honour is this to the nature of man, <hi>What am I,</hi> ſaies the Prophet <hi>David, and what's my fathers houſe to be the Kings ſonne in law!</hi> nay what are we poore creatures, to finde this acceptance with the King of glory! yea, how juſtly may we admire it in the words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David, Lord, what is man that thou art mindful of him &amp;c!</hi> for in this communion of God, what can we want? why, God ſhall be all and all unto us, he ſhall be beauty for the eye, muſick for the eare, honey for the taſte, the full content and ſatisfaction of our deſires, and that immediately from himſelfe. True it is, God is all in all in this world, <hi>In him we live, and move, and have our being,</hi> but here he works by meanes, and ſecondary cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, here he gives wine to make glad the heart, and oile, &amp;c. but there all intervening means between God and us is removed, <hi>With thee is the well of life, and in thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight ſhall we ſee light;</hi> not in the light of the Sunne, or the light of a candle, there is no need of them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.4. but in thy light, the light of God himſelfe, yea the whole life of glory, together with all the concomitants of it, flows from him, as the ſole and original fountaine of it. O how
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118106:14"/>ſweet muſt that happineſſe be that is ſo derived. Secondly, as we have communion with God, ſo with Jeſus Chriſt the Mediator of the new Covenant, <hi>We ſhall ſee him as he is,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. To ſee Chriſt in our natures, he that was ſo deſpiſed of men, a man of ſorrowes, that laid down his life for us, whom we have ſerved, and profeſt againſt all the oppoſition of the world, to ſee him (I ſay) ſo advanced ſitting at the right hand of God, farre above all principalities and powers, muſt needs be an happy viſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; If the wiſe-men (upon his nativity) ſo rejoyced to ſee the ſtarre, that led them to the place where he was; although he was then in a ſtate of humiliation, in a ſtable amongſt brute beaſts, what joy will it be to his ſervants, whoſe ſoules are inamoured on him, to ſee him in the higheſt Heavens? In a word, not to inſtance in particulars, here's a bleſſed communion with all the bleſſed company of Heaven; <hi>Many ſhall come from the Eaſt and Weſt, and ſit down with Abraham, Iſaac, and Jacob, in the Kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> Now what that will avail the ſaints, may appeare. Firſt from the purity, and holineſſe of that bleſſed company; <hi>Without ſhall be dogs, and inchanters, &amp;c.</hi> there is no bad company there to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect or infeſt, all ſuch are turned down into the lake that burns with fire and brim-ſtone: no, there is none but ſaints, they are all the ſervants of God, and his name is in their fore-heads, and therefore if holineſſe be in acceptance, there it dwells in its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. Secondly, from their ſtate and quality; there are no mean perſons there to commerce with, there's none but Angels, and Archangels, none but Patriarchs, Prophets, Apoſtles, none but Kings, and Prieſts, the meaneſt perſon there is poſſeſſor of a crown, not an earthly, corruptible crown, but a crown of endleſſe and immortal glory. Thirdly, from their charity. Affection here is mutable, and liable to alteration, whom we love to day, we may hate to morrow, but there charity abideth alway, every one rejoycing in one anothers happineſſe: as they are perfectly ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and have a full communion with God, ſo their charity is <hi>ſummo gradu,</hi> abſolute and perfect indeed. And thus you ſee, what this life is in reſpect of the aſſociation and fellowſhip with it. Laſtly, what this life of glory is, you may conjecture from the immunities and priviledges of it: for brevity ſake, I will referre them to theſe three; the firſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the abſence of all evil, <hi>Bleſſed are they that die in the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> As for deſeaſes,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118106:15"/>aches, paines, the labours of this life, they have an eternal Sabbath, there's no teares. The ſecond is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the adjection of all good things. Tell me, what would you have for the body, or the ſoul? would you have this mortal to put on immortality, this corruptible to put on incorruption, would you have this natural body to be ſpiritual? to be a glorious body? to ſhine as the Sunne, to be like the glorious body of Chriſt? or for the ſoul, what happineſſe can you expect? whereas ſhe is depraved with actuall and original ſinne, would you have her pure, and imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate, whereas ſhe's liable to infirmities, imperfections, &amp;c? would you have her accompliſht with perfect righteouſneſſe, perfect knowledge perfect liberty, perfect charity? would you have her to know God, as we are known, to ſee him face to face? <hi>Quicquid deſiberabitur, ibi aderit, &amp; quicquid aderit perfectum erit,</hi> whatſoever our deſires can extend unto ſhall be preſent, and that in perfection. Laſtly, an eternal and immutable abode in our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe. <hi>In thy preſence is the fulneſſe of joy, and pleaſures for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more;</hi> there are many and comfortable bleſſings to be had in this world, but then as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of riches, <hi>they betake themſelves to their wings, and fly away as Eagles,</hi> there is an uncertainty, an inſtability attends them; had you the ſtrength of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> the time will come when the keepers of the houſe ſhall tremble, and ſtrong men bow themſelves; had you the wiſdome of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the time of dotage is before you, a time when all your thoughts muſt periſh; had you the baeuty of <hi>Abſolom,</hi> the time will come when the painted duſt of the complexion muſt be corrupted into the putrifactive duſt of the grave but be intereſted in this happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and eternity goes along with you, in will ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de with you more millions of years then there are piles of graſſe upon the face of the earth, or drops of water in the ocean, even whileſt God is God. And thus as <hi>Moſes</hi> from the top of <hi>Nebo</hi> had ſome view of the temporal <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſo from theſe and the like meditations, you may apprehend ſome glimpſe of this promiſed land, the filicity of the ſaints in the land of the living; But as <hi>Solomons</hi> Royalty and State was but, in part related to the Queen of <hi>Sheha,</hi> ſo the leaſt punctillio of this glorious condition hath ſcarce been diſcovered. O that in the thoughts of it, we might ever after be enamoured on it, ever after order our lives and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations to the attainment of it.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118106:15"/>
            <p>Now as all this relates to Chriſt as the meritorious cauſe of the ſame, we may hence learn with what love, what delight, what ſtirring affections we ought to devote our ſelves to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of our bleſſed Saviour. If the rich glutton (<hi>Luk.</hi> 16.19.) from the extremity of his helliſh torments, was ſo deſirous of a drop of water to coole the tip of his tongue; what would he have given for a full and plenary delivery from that accurſed place? had he apprehended any poſſibility (through the merits of him that hath the keyes of hell and of death in whom there is no condemnation) that he might have been tranſlated from that miſerable condition into a ſtate of bliſſe, ſuch a life as this, would he (think you) have ſlighted ſuch a redeemer? or rather in full admiration of him, (having now by that fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, thoſe unſpeakable torments experimentally learn'd the worth of ſalvation in the abſence of it) would he not have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured by all meanes poſſible to have gain'd ſome intereſt in him? But alas! there was no ſuch redemption now to be expected, for the outworking of his ſalvation: he had an opportune fitting time allowed him, whil'ſt he was on earth, but now being in hell there is an invincible gulfe fixt between him and Heaven, ſuch a ſeparation as ſhall divide and keep him off from all happineſſe, and that (which is a confounding, heart-breaking word) for all eternity. Now if the grace of Chriſt be of that concernment (to the attainment wherof the time of this life is the ſole and only allotted ſeaſon) why then, conſider and be wiſe for thy ſelf, whileſt thou haſt exiſtence and being in this land of the living, thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitation in <hi>Sion;</hi> whilſt wiſdomes gates are ſet open to thee, her invitations ſo importunate with thee; let it be thy greateſt care to improve theſe faire opportunities to the good of thy ſoul, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thoſe proffers of grace, and in due time to lay hold on him that is thine advocate, thine hope, thy peace, thy ſole and only Saviour; otherwiſe it ſhall come to paſſe, that thou ſhalt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment over thy forlorne ſoule, as Chriſt did once over unhappy <hi>Jeruſalem, O that thou hadſt known the things that belong, unto thy peace, Luk.</hi> 19.42. And here to remove ſuch obſtacles as the wiſdome of the fleſh (that wiſdome that is enmity againſt God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. fooliſhneſſe with God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.19. death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.6.) may caſt in thy way to impede and hinder thee in thy way and progreſſe to Chriſt, (ſay) wherein doſt thou take, exception
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118106:16"/>at the name and profeſſion of Chriſt? Art thou not in the firſt place offended at the alteration, and change he requires in his converts, becauſe they be all new creatures? men of another faſhion? bidding adieu to their former vanities? true it is, as he is the King of ſaints, holy and immaculate in himſelfe; ſo he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects holineſſe in all his followers; they that are his muſt crucifie the fleſh, with the corruptions and luſts of it. And doth not this go hard with corrupt nature, that takes no content but in the pleaſures of ſinne? This it was that troubled St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> at the time of his converſion; <hi>Dimittéſne nos, &amp; ab hoc momento non erimus tecum ultra in aeternum?</hi> what wilt thou (ſpeaking under the name of his former ſenſual delights and pleaſures) wilt thou caſhiere and abandon us for ever? ſhall we even at this inſtant take our leaves of thee, and be with thee no more for ever? But how comes it to paſſe of at thou art ſo beſotted, ſo bewitched with the baſeneſſe of ſinne, which is nought but filthineſſe? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. nought but abomination, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.9. ſo filthy, ſo abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that it makes us a deriſion to our neighbours, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.8. an abomination to the Saints, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29 <hi>ult.</hi> an abhorring to all fleſh, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 66.24. yea to God himſelfe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.6. the locuſts, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.8. had the faces of men, and haire as the haire of women, but the teeth of lions, and tailes of ſcorpions; herein ſee the picture and embleme of thy ſinnes, (how lovely ſoever they ſeem in their appearance) thou ſhalt finde to thine intolerable anguiſh, they have lions teeth to torment thine offended, polluted conſcience, and the ſcorpions tayles to wound and ſting thee to death. Had <hi>Amaſa</hi> known that <hi>Joab</hi> had come to murther him, he would have kept a further diſtance from him notwithſtanding all his faire ſalutes and fawning complements; why, behold, every ſinne (how inſinuating ſoever) is a murtherer, and comes to ſlay thee, and therefore inſtead of that fatall, unhappy way of ſinne, learn to know the way of holineſſe, where no lion nor ravenous beaſt ſhall be found, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 35.9. Or in the ſecond place, art thou troubled at the condition of his Kingdome, becauſe it is not of this world? <hi>John</hi> 18.36. becauſe the profeſſion of his name expoſes to every mans hatred, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.22. becauſe a godly life (ſuch a life as he requires) is liable to perſecution, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> to gain followers to his party, made a proclamation (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> tells us) that whoſoever would
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118106:16"/>follow him to the warres, if he were a footman, he ſhould be made a horſeman, if an horſeman, he ſhould have a chariot, if he had a cottage, he ſhould have a village, if a village, he ſhould have a city, if he were Lord of a city he ſhould be a Prince of a region, or countrey; and as for gold, he would poure it out by heapes, <hi>ſans nombre.</hi> But now the invitation that Chriſt tenders to the world runner in a quite oppoſite ſtraine; <hi>If any man will come after me, let him deny himſelfe and take up his croſſe daily and follow me, Luk.</hi> 9.23. and therefore the men of the world (that have their portion in this life, that minde earthly things, and know no happineſſe beyond the increaſe of corne, wine, and oile) cannot brook ſuch a maſter. But herein (for an antidote to this diſcouragement) conſider in the firſt place the vani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y and emptineſſe of all earthly, and terrene things; to them that ſtand upon the top of the <hi>Alpes,</hi> the great cities of <hi>Campania</hi> (they ſay) ſeem but as mole-hills in their appearance; ſo were thy converſion in heaven, were thine affections implant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on things ſupernal, and above; didſt thou converſe with God, thou would<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt then ſee no great matter in the world why thou ſhould'ſt be ſo enamoured on it; thou would'ſt then diſcerne not only how uncertaine thoſe inferiour comforts are for their continuance, betaking themſelves to their wings, and flying away like Eagles, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of riches, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.5. but likewiſe for their uſe and imployment how utterly unable they are to make thee an happy man. <hi>Non domus aut ſundus, &amp;c.</hi> If neither houſe, nor land, nor heaps of gold, or ſilver (as the Poet ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved) can cure the diſeaſes of the body, what then can theſe things availe thee to the good of thy ſoul? had a man all the Kingdomes of the world, and the glory of them, they could not purchaſe the leaſt meaſure of faith, of aſſurance of Gods love, of grace, or of ſpiritual comfort for us; no, oft-times they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damage and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rejudice the ſouls welfare, choak the ſeed of the word, and ſteal away the heart from God. Secondly, conſider how Chriſtianity and Religion takes not away the comfortable uſe of the creatures, but only regulates the ſame by its ſubjection to Gods glory, and the good of our ſoules. It's reported of the Kings of <hi>Mexico,</hi> that it was their faſhion alwayes to be carried aloft and upon mens ſhoulders, and never to touch the ground; and it is related of the King of <hi>Japan,</hi> that if he tread upon the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118106:17"/>ſearth, he forfeits his regality and place. God hath not dealt co ſtrictly with us, we may make bold with the earth, we may comfort our ſelves in the deſirable things of the world, only out are muſt be this, that we ſink not into the earth, that we ly not buried under it, that we loſe not the Creator in the creature, our future happineſſe in our preſent fruition: it's only the, immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, irregular love of the world that is inconſiſtent with the love of Chriſt; according to that of our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>He that loveth father or mother more then me, is not worthy of me, Matth.</hi> 10.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Thirdly, conſider what a happy recompence betides ſuch ſufferings: hadſt thou ſuch an eye of faith as the Iſraelites had in <hi>Egypt,</hi> when through that houſe of bondage, that iron furnace, through the ſea, the wilderneſſe, whole armies of the ſonnes of <hi>Anak,</hi> they could ſee a land of promiſe; or as <hi>Job</hi> had, that could apprehend a Redeemer, a reſurrection, a reſtitution through a dunghill, through the diſcomforts of his friends, the temptations of his wife, malice of Satan, changes and armies of ſorrowes; or as St. <hi>Stephen</hi> had, when through a tempeſt of ſtones he could ſee the heavens open, then thou would'ſt rejoyce (according to the paterne of the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.41.) that thou art counted worthy to ſuffer rebuke for his name; what an happy iſſue attends ſuch afflictions, you may ſee the Apoſtle tells us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. For affliction, here's glory, for light afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a weight of glory, for <hi>affliction which is but for a moment, a farre more exceeding and eternal weight of glory.</hi> Or in the third place, doth not the example of the world pervert thee, and keep thee at a diſtance from him? is not the unbeliefe of Rulers and Phariſees a ground of their infidelity? Is not that oppoſition of Kings and Princes, heathen and people the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks of in the ſecond Pſalme, an argument to confirm and ſtrengthen thee in thine enmity againſt him? It was the ſaying of <hi>Huſhai</hi> to <hi>Abſolom,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Whom this people and all the men of</hi> Iſrael <hi>choſe, his will I be, and with him will I dwell.</hi> So in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Religion, men are reſolved not to be ſingular, but to apply themſelves according to the way of the multitude. It was ſaid of <hi>Alcibiades</hi> a Noble man of <hi>Athens,</hi> that he was <hi>omnium hora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum homo,</hi> a man for all companies, all times, and circumſtances; that he was laborious amongſt the <hi>Syracuſians,</hi> but looſly carried amongſt the more diſſolute <hi>Athenians,</hi> grave and ſober amongſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118106:17"/>the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> but intemperate amongſt the <hi>Thracians,</hi> &amp; effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate amongſt the <hi>Perſians;</hi> ſo in reference to religion corrupt nature, that ſavours not the things of the Spirit, knowes (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſame faſhion) how to garbe and apply her ſelfe to all factions, all opinions, all formes, all times how oppoſite ſoever they be to the Scepter of Chriſt, yea, ſhe deems it her wiſdome never to profeſſe more of Chriſt then may ſtand with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation and allowance of popular acceptance: well, but what will this correſpondency with the multitude availe thee, when God comes to viſite thee for thy ſinne? <hi>Though hand joyn in hand, the wicked ſhall not be unpuniſhed, Proverbs</hi> 11.21. and when <hi>the wicked ſhall be turned into hell, and all the people that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God;</hi> who will acquit thee? the counſell of the ungodly may be pleaſing, the way of ſinners delightful, the chaire of ſcorners eaſie, but he only is the bleſſed man that ſtudies the avoidance of them. Laſtly, art thou not offended at the intereſt and propriety, he challenges in thee, as the ſole and only Monarch over thee? becauſe he requires all thine heart, all thy ſtrength, all thy ſoul, admitting no conſort, no corrival to ſhare with thee in the ſame? It's ſaid of the Ido atrous heathen that were placed in <hi>Samaria, that they feared the Lord,</hi> but ſerved their own gods too, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.33. upon the like tearmes if Chriſt (accepting ſome formality for himſelfe) would diſpenſe with the ſonnes or men to live to their former luſts, to perſiſt ſtill in the ſervice of ſinne and Satan (their old maſters under whoſe juriſdictions they have been born, and bred,) he would then with fairer acceptance be admitted, but becauſe he will be abſolute and alone in his govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe he affoards no place for covetouſneſſe to reigne, drunkenneſſe to rage, oathes and blaſphemies to domineere, the world cannot away with him, this amongſt others was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why, when <hi>Taberius</hi> propounded him to the Romane Senate (with the priviledgcs of his own ſuffrage) to be worſhipped for a God, they rejected him, becauſe according to his own rules he would be God alone. But <hi>O fooliſh people, and unwiſe, do you ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite the Lord?</hi> (as <hi>Moſes</hi> expoſtulated with the ungrateful Iſraelites, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.6.) <hi>Is not he thy Father that bought thee? hath not he made chee, and eſtabliſhed thee?</hi> If he be all, and all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, in this way of thine happineſſe, why ſhouldeſt thou not with an whole, unſhared, incommunicable love devote thy ſelfe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118106:18"/>to him in the way of homage and ſubjection? In a word, whatſoever thy temptations, thy diſcouragements be, break thorow all difficulties, <hi>and then it ſhall come to paſſe that when the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and unbelieving, &amp;c ſhall have their part in the lake that burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with fire and brimſtone,</hi> thou ſhalt finde thy ſelfe in a ſtate of happineſſe, yea, <hi>he that overcometh, ſhall inherit all things, Rev.</hi> 21.7.</p>
            <p>Now for the third particular in my text, the endeavour of a Chriſtian about the attainment of the ſame, <hi>Who ſo findeth:</hi>]</p>
            <p>The finding here ſpoken of is not accidental, or caſual; but ſuch a finding as preſuppoſeth inquiſition, and ſearch: He that by harkening to this wiſdome, by hearing her inſtruction, by watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing daily at her gates, by giving attendance at the poſts of her doors, by keeping her wayes as the holy Spirit enjoynes in the precedent verſes; he that ſhall thus ſeek her, he ſhall finde her, and he that findeth her, <hi>findeth life.</hi> Whence you may note,</p>
            <p>¶ That where there is a due and right ſeeking of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, together with all theſe ineſtimable bleſſings im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported in him, there in due time ſhall be a comfortable and bleſſed finding of him.</p>
            <p>This was the argument of <hi>Solomon,</hi> to impreſſe upon us the ſtudy of wiſdome, <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.4. <hi>If thou ſeek for her, &amp;c.</hi> In the words you ſee how a Chriſtian ſhould beſtow himſelfe that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects wiſdome, he muſt ſeek and ſearch, and that with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, as for things moſt precious, and then the iſſue and event follows, <hi>Then ſhalt thou finde, &amp;c.</hi> So, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.7. <hi>To them that by continuance in well-doing ſeek, &amp;c.</hi> So, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.25. <hi>The Lord is good to them that trust in him, and to the ſoul that ſeeketh him.</hi> And ſo it muſt needs be, faithful ſeeking, can never finde God defective in granting. Firſt becauſe he is a gracious God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in the proſperity of his ſervants. It's the argument of our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>If you that are evil can give good gifts, &amp;c. Matth</hi> 7.11. evil in compariſon of God, who is infinitely, and eſſentially good; evil in the inclination of our hearts, which in all their thoughts and imaginations are evil continually, if you know how to give good gifts, things requiſite and neceſſary, how much more, &amp;c? Secondly, becauſe his glory depends upon it, if Gods people ſhould waite upon him in the way of his ordinances, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118106:18"/>ſerve him, as he in his word hath preſcribed, and then if God ſhould not accommodate himſelfe unto him, in what they ſeek; who would waite upon him any longer? whoſe mouths would not be opened with thoſe Atheiſts, in <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. <hi>It's in vaine to ſerve God, &amp;c?</hi> But now when God reveales the meanes of grace, gives us hearts to apply our ſelves unto them, and then gives his bleſſing upon the ſame, this is an obligation to his praiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.26. <hi>They that ſeek after the Lord, ſhall praiſe him.</hi> Thirdly, becauſe it is the preſcribed way for finding: the meanes that God hath deputed muſt needs be effectual, but this is Gods way, <hi>Aske, and ye ſhall have, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſhewes in the firſt place the vanity and emptineſſe of their hopes, that expect theſe ineſtimable treaſures without any paines<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking in the wayes of God; although they reſtreine prayer from the Almighty, prophane the Sabbaths, habitually neglect all holy duties, yet they doubt not of Gods favour, queſtion not their future happineſſe and ſalvation. But were not he ſtrangely conceited that ſhould expect victory, triumphs, ſpoiles, that was never in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mes? the depths of knowledge, that never opened book? the return of a good voyage, that never put himſelfe upon the adventure? a plentiful harveſt, that affoarded no tillage to the ſoile? No, <hi>Dii laboribus omnia vendunt,</hi> was a proverb amongſt the heathen; all the bleſſings we have are from God, yet obteined only by labour, and paines, in the uſe of the meanes. <hi>The ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> (ſaies <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>ſhall be clothed with rags. And he that will not worke muſt not eat,</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle, 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.10. ſo for ſpiritual things, he that ſeekes not to God in the preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed way of his worſhip, can expect nothing but the rags and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of ſpiritual poverty to betide him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it ſhews the happy iſſue and event of all holy endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. In the things of this world, a man may ſeek with much dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and never obteine; a man may go to the Phyſician expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing health, but finde death; to the Lawyer for juſtice, but finde oppreſſion, and wrong; to his friend for acceptance, like <hi>Joſeph</hi> to his brethren, but finde enmity and malice: <hi>But the Lord is nigh unto them that call upon him, all them that call upon him faithfully;</hi> the gate of heaven ever ſtands open to ſuch ſeekers, they may go with boldneſſe to the throne of grace; Gods eare is never weary of hearing their ſuites, like welcome favourites
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118106:19"/>their petitions ſhall be granted. And therefore in the third place, let it be an encouragement to us (as we deſire to proſper in the things of God) ſo to ſeek unto him for the ſame; <hi>They that know thy name, will put their truſt in thee, Pſal.</hi> 9 10. why? <hi>Thou Lord never failest them that ſeek thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus we come to the laſt particular in my text, &amp; that is the party intereſſed in this happineſs, and that is ſet down indefinitely and without limitation, <hi>Whoſe findeth, &amp;c.</hi> whence you may note,</p>
            <p>¶ The equality and indifferency of Gods acceptance to all ſorts and conditions of people.</p>
            <p>As it is not honours, preferments, greatneſſe, on the one ſide that commends us to Gods favour: ſo on the other it is not afflictions, wants, neceſſities, outward baſeneſſe, that makes us more deſpicable in his ſight, whether we be high, or low, rich, or poore, it matters not, Jew, or Gentile, Scythian, Barbarian, bond, and free, are all one in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>And therefore in the firſt place, let not great men pride them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the things of this life, theſe are but common bleſſings, argue only Gods general goodneſſe, not his eſpecial mercy; It is not a man of quality <hi>(quatenus talis)</hi> becauſe he is thus, and thus endowed, that findes theſe treaſures, but man, preciſely man, bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered, without any reſpect had to theſe outward endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; And therefore, <hi>Let not the wiſe man glory in his wiſdome, nor the rich man, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The conſideration hereof in the ſecond place, may encourage poore men to ſeek after God, and to devote themſelves to his ſervice; Art thou baſe and contemptible in the eyes of the world? it matters not, thou mayeſt be a veſſel of honour, an h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ire of life; as well as the greateſt Emperour, or Monarch in the world, yea, in ſeeking the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, this uncreated wiſdome of God, thou as well as any other mayeſt finde him, and in him <hi>Life;</hi> It's intayled to none, but left for all ſeekers in general; <hi>Whoſo findeth me, findeth life.</hi> And thus I have done with my text,</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118106:19"/>
            <head>Courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>TO ſatisfie the deſires of ſome that requeſted the ſame, I have (not without ſome reluctant backwardneſſe) annexed this enſuing exhortation delivered at the enterrement of the deceaſed Lady, whoſe death occaſioned this Sermon. The Hebrew word for a grave or ſepulchre is from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ask, require, or expect, to intimate peradventure how the grave with its open, inhiant mouth, ſeems to invite paſſengers to its entertainment. True it is, we cannot long withſtand its ſummons, not long fruſtrate its expectation, all of us (how ſoon we know not) muſt take up our lodgings there, and make our beds in the dark; and therefore in all holy foreſight of the ſame, it behooves us to fit, and prepare our ſelves for ſuch a change, to this purpoſe, if theſe ſhort directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, may any way availe thee, (howſoever I hazard my ſelfe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy cenſure) I ſhall not repent the tender of them to thy view.</p>
            <p>There is no eſtate nor condition of men, or women whatſoever, or howſoever qualified, that can ſecure themſelves from the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no, be they what they will be, ſooner or later they muſt be going, they muſt all to their long home. This is a theame that the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> muſt proclame, yea becauſe mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dull of hearing, he muſt crie it out, as you ſee, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 40.6. <hi>All fleſh is graſſe, and the grace, &amp;c.</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, Art thou ſtrong and luſty as an Eagle? <hi>Are thy breaſts full of milk,</hi> (as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>thy bones full of marrow?</hi> let thy fleſh be what it will, it is but graſſe, and muſt wither. Haſt thou all the endowments of nature, all the ornaments of education, dexterity of wit, ſolidity of judgement, ſtrength of memory, readineſſe of expreſſion, or the like, together with the abundance of theſe outward bleſſings? why, all this is but a flower, and muſt fade; this we may demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate from all the generations that in the ſeveral ages of the world, have been before us; what is become of them all? what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s become of the Giants before the flood? of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ob,</hi> and the bleſſed Patriarchs, before the law? of all thoſe mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itudes, and many thouſands that came out of <hi>Egypt?</hi> of all thoſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118106:20"/>innumerable millions that have lived ſince their dayes? as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Zachary</hi> propounds the quere, <hi>Zaob.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Your fathers where are they, and do the Prophets live for ever?</hi> No, they do not; no there is a ſtatute law againſt us all, <hi>Statutum eſt; It is appointed for all men once to die, Heb.</hi> 9.27. Let <hi>Solomon</hi> be wiſe, <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſtrong, <hi>Abſolom</hi> beautifull, all availes not. An inſtance hereof to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we have in this preſent ſpectacle of mortality; what variety of bleſſings in a moſt plentifull and liberal meaſure did God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon her? here was <hi>Bona corporis,</hi> a firme and healthful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of body; <hi>Bona animae,</hi> all intellectual abilities and endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; <hi>Bona fortunae,</hi> eſtate and meanes anſwerable to her ranck and quality; And together with all theſe how did God bleſſe her in ſuch an husband that all honoured Sir <hi>John Read?</hi> in ſuch a kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and aliance? in ſuch an off-ſpring? ſuch children and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren children? how did God exalt her in making her ſuch a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? ſuch a Grand mother? to affoard her ſuch branches from her ſelfe, ſo lovely, ſo faire and flouriſhing? to have ſuch an iſſue ſo accompliſht, ſo demean'd, ſo ordered both towar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s God and man? what a comfort ſhe felt in this particular (verifying that of <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 10.1.) ſhe lately in her ſickneſſe acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that with all thankfulneſſe. To theſe I might adde the ſplendor of her vertues, which with an humble reverent ſilence, I chuſe rather to leave to the ingenuous approbation of others judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then by the ſcant and imperfect expreſſions of my weak Rhetorick to impaire. What a ſweet and gratefull influence theſe diffuſive vertues had upon you according to you ſeveral occaſions and wants, I need not tell you; what mean theſe ſad looks? theſe dejected countenances? theſe overflowing eyes? the crowded preſſe of this preſent auditory? every one (to ſpeak in the phraſe of <hi>Job</hi>) <hi>having his harp turned into mourning and his Organ into the voice of them that weep?</hi> In all theſe you ſhew how you prized her, how precious ſhe was unto you, what an eſtimate you ſet upon her deſerts: but now in the approach of death, all theſe ſweet mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, all theſe faire and rich enjoyments, all her acceptance and grace in the world could not purchaſe for her (beyond her ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time) the leaſt minute to her further abode. True it is, this is a common point, a granted truth, there is none ſo fooliſh as to deny it; but as known and common as it is, let me aske you, who ponders it? who conſiders it in his heart? who fits and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118106:20"/>himſelf accordingly? It was ſaid of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> that <hi>he had gray haires here and there, and knew not of them, Hoſ.</hi> 7.9. Is it not ſo with our ſelves? let the ſignes and ſymptoms of mortality be apparent, are we not utterly heedleſſe and forgetful of them? true it is, whileſt the ſound of a paſſing bell is in our eares, whileſt the mourners are abroad in the ſtreets, whileſt we are within the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of a funeral ſermon, oh then we are touched with ſome paſſionate meditations, and thoughts, ſuch as theſe; oh the ſting of death, oh the ſeverity of Gods tribunal, the ſtrictneſſe of the accompt, oh the depth of hell, oh that I could make my peace with God, that it might go well with me in my latter end. But when theſe viſible ſignes, theſe ſenſible objects are no ſooner remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but we are ſtill the ſame we were before; juſt like the doves and daws in the ſteeple, in the beginning of a peale, they ſeem in a kind of an affright to betake themſelves to their wings, and fly aloft, but preſently the bells are no ſooner ceaſed, but they return again to their holes, and are as ſecure as ever they were before. But oh that Gods people were wiſe, that they would conſider their latter end. It is the ſaying of <hi>Auguſtine, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam in quovis loco de gehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na diceretur, in gehenuam prohiberet incidiſſe:</hi> I would men were ever talking of hell, it would be a meanes to keep them from it; ſo for death, the more ſerious we are in the thoughts of it, the more ſafe from the danger of it; and therefore with <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> let us make our ſepulchres in our gardens, be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the meditations of death at all times, even amongſt our ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efeſt delights; And that we may proſper in the thoughts of it, let me commend unto you theſe particulars. Firſt, diſpatch and haſten thy repentance; <hi>Non bonum eſt in eo ſtatu vivere, in quo non eſt tutum mori.</hi> Doſt thou live in a ſtate of ſinne, uncleanneſſe, wantonneſſe prophaneneſſe &amp;c? why, think with thy ſelfe, wouldſt thou dye in ſuch a condition? hath not the Lord denounced it, that the unrighteous ſhall never enter the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? why, then if thou wouldſt fit thy ſelfe for death, thou muſt purge thy conſcience from dead works, <hi>crucifie the fleſh, with the corruptions and luſts of it.</hi> Secondly, thou muſt ſet thy ſelfe about the performance of all holy daties, thou muſt do that good which may be for good to thy ſoul for the future. <hi>The time of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture is at hand,</hi> (faies the Apoſtle) what then? doth not the Apoſtle tremble? no, the conſideration of his life paſt ſupports
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118106:21"/>him, <hi>I have faught the good fight, &amp;c.</hi> Thirdly; thou muſt ſtudy to be built up in him, who is <hi>The Lord our righteouſneſſe,</hi> doſt thou reſt upon inferiour things? thou ſhalt be as the heath in the wilderneſſe, and ſhalt not ſee when good comes; but if thou reſt upon Chriſt; as the maine foundation-ſtone, thou ſhalt not be confounded, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 28, 16. Laſtly, go unto God in prayer, that he would help thee, and further thee in this thy preparation; <hi>O teach us to number our dayes, &amp;c.</hi> we cannot number them rightly, except God help us; and therefore in the title of that Pſalme, you have it ſtiled by the name of a prayer, <hi>A prayer of</hi> Moſes <hi>the man of God;</hi> to ſhew how we ſhould be affected in thoughts, as likewiſe that it is God only that enables us in the the ſame. And herein we muſt take heed to ſet upon theſe, and the like preparations ſpeedily, and without delay; <hi>Hoc momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt unde pendet aeternitas,</hi> the time of this life is but a moment, but ſuch a moment, as hath all eternity depending upon it. It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated of <hi>Caeſar Borgia,</hi> that he ſpoke it upon his death bed, that he had ſtudied to prevent all inconveniences that might betide him, but death; but as for that he did not think it had been ſo neer him; let not his caſe be thine, but rather let thy reſolution conſpire with <hi>Jobs, to waite all the dayes of thine appointed time till thy change come.</hi> I conclude all with that of St. <hi>John, Revel.</hi> 20.6. <hi>Bleſſed, and holy is he, that hath part in the firſt reſurrection, on ſuch the ſecond death hath no power.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118106:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
